Charlotte J. Lambert

cjl8@illinois.edu · charlottelambert.github.io

Research Objective

My research is at the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction and Natural Language Processing. I work on examining factors that contribute to healthy and unhealthy online conversations. Specifically, I am working to devise proactive methods for encouraging strong conversations that are resilient to adverse behavior. My research aims to make online spaces more welcoming to its users through the encouragement of healthy behaviors and improved methods of moderation. Broadly, my interests are at the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction and Natural Language Processing. Currently, my focus is on examining factors that contribute to healthy and unhealthy online conversations. Specifically, I am working on devising proactive methods to facilitate online conversations that are resilient to the influence of adverse behavior.

Keywords: Online communities, social computing, healthy behaviors, moderation

Education

• University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign Ph.D. in Computer Science

Urbana, IL 2020-present

- Advisor: Eshwar Chandrasekharan
- Research Interests: Social Computing, Natural Language Processing

Vassar College
 Bachelor of Arts in Computer Science, Minors in Mathematics and Italian; GPA: 3.9/4.0

Poughkeepsie, NY 2016-2020

- Thesis: Temporal Exploration of the Proceedings of Old Bailey
- Research Advisors: Jonathan Gordon and Jennifer Walter

Publications

- Inter-Sense: An Investigation of Sensory Blending in Fiction. In First International Workshop on Multisensory
 Data & Knowledge: The 3rd Conference on Language, Data and Knowledge (2021)
 Corina R. Girju and Charlotte Lambert
- Conversation-Level Resilience. Poster in the First Workshop on NLP for Positive Impact: ACL-IJCNLP 2021 Charlotte Lambert and Eshwar Chandrasekharan
- Story Immersion: Toward Fiction Synesthesia for Enhanced Reader Empathy. Presentation in Uncommon Senses Conference (2021)

Corina R. Girju and Charlotte Lambert

Awards and Honors

• **Saburo Muroga Endowed Fellowship**, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign *Fellowship awarded to outstanding graduate students in computer science.*

2020-2021

• **Graduated with Departmental Honors**, Vassar College Honors awarded to students nominated by the Computer Science Department for academic excellence.

2020

• **Graduated with General Honors**, Vassar College Honors awarded to the top 20% of the graduating class

2020

Honors awarded to the top 20% of the graduating class.

2020

Honorary Sigma Xi Nomination, Vassar College
 Awarded to graduating seniors nominated based upon their research accomplishments and academic record.

Research Experience

• Graduate Research Assistant Department of Computer Science, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign Urbana, IL Fall 2021

- Advisor: Eshwar Chandrasekharan
- Project: Conversation-Level Resilience to Bad Actors in Reddit Communities
- Area of Work: Human-Computer Interaction

Undergraduate Research AssistantDepartment of Computer Science, Vassar College

Poughkeepsie, NY 2018-2020

- Advisor: Jonathan Gordon; Project: Computational Models of Literary Variation
- Assisted on projects related to natural language processing
- Analyzed patterns in data collected about the use of language in a corpus of books
- Area of Work: Natural Language Processing

• Distributed Research Experiences for Undergraduates (DREU) Intern Department of Computer Science, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Urbana, IL Summer 2019

- Advisor: Julia Hockenmaier; Project: Collaborative Dialogue in Minecraft
- Started building fully interactive agents to communicate using natural language in a 3D environment
- Used concepts in NLP and deep learning to improve quality of utterances generated by two agents
- Worked on neural network to recognize shapes in 3D with nearly 100% accuracy
- Area of Work: Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning

Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Intern University of Southern California Institute for Creative Technologies

Los Angeles, CA Summer 2018

- Advisor: Jonathan Gratch, Gale Lucas; Project: Impact of AI on User Psychology
- Developed and optimized code to support a system to be used to carry out a future study
- Worked to create realistic AI capable of negotiating online with users and other AIs
- Area of Work: Artificial Intelligence

Teaching Experience

Discrete Math (CS 173)
 Teaching Assistant, Instructors: Dr. Margaret Fleck, Dr. Carl Evans
 Guide weekly group discussions for seven groups of approx. 6 students; Evaluate weekly exams; Hold weekly office bours

• Introduction to Computer Science (CS 125)

Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Dr. Geoffrey Challen

Co-led an optional weekly recap of course material for between 50 and 100 undergraduates.

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Fall 2020

Professional Service and Volunteering

• Girls Who Code Facilitator
University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

2021-present

• Sub-reviewer "AAAI-MAKE: Combining Machine Learning and Knowledge Engineering Practice," AAAI Spring Symposium 2020, Stanford University

Languages

Italian (proficient); Spanish (reading)

Programming

Python, Java, LATEX, C/C++, R, Matlab, Dr Racket/Scheme